上一节我们看了如何构建公钥加密，根据陷门函数
In the previous segment we saw how to
build public key encryption from trapdoor
本节我们要构建一个经典的陷门函数叫做RSA
functions, in this segment we're going to
build a classic trapdoor function called
但首先我们快速回顾一下，什么是陷门函数
RSA. But first let's quickly review what a
trapdoor function is. So recall that a
一个陷门函数由三个算法组成
trapdoor function is made up of three
algorithms. There is a key generation
一个密钥生成算法，陷门函数本身，以及陷门函数的逆
algorithm, the function itself, and the
inverse of the function. The key
密钥生成算法输出一个公钥和一个私钥。在这里
generation algorithm outputs a public key
and a secret key. And in this case, in
本讲中公钥将定义一个函数，将集合X映射到它自身
this lecture the public key is going to
define a function that maps the set X onto
这就是我为什么叫这些陷门函数为陷门置换
itself. Which is why I call these things
trapdoor permutations, as opposed to
而不叫陷门函数，因为这个函数将X映射到他自身
trapdoor functions, simply because the
function maps X onto itself, whereas a
而陷门函数可以将集合X映射到一个任意集合Y
trapdoor function might map the set X to
some arbitrary set Y. Now given the public
现在给定公钥，陷门函数，如我们所说，定义了
从集合X映射到X的函数
key, the function, as we say, basically
defines this function from the set X to
那么给定私钥，我们可以求这个函数的逆
the set X. And then given the secret key,
we can invert this function. So this
这个函数F从正方向计算了这个函数
function F evaluates the function in the
forward direction, and this function F
而这个F的逆，意味着用私钥SK，可以从反方向计算F
inverse, which means the secret key SK,
computes F in the reverse direction. Now
现在我们说这个陷门置换是安全的，如果由公钥定义的函数
we say that the trapdoor permutation is
secure if the function defined by the
事实上是一个单向函数，意味着它是容易计算的
public key is in fact a one-way function,
which means that it's easy to evaluate,
但如果没有陷门（私钥是陷门），是很难求逆的
but without the trapdoor, the secret
trapdoor, it's difficult to invert. Before
在我们看第一个陷门置换之前，我想简单回顾一下
we look at our first example of a trapdoor
permutation, I want to do a quick review
一些我们需要的必要的算术事实。特别是
of some necessary arithmetic facts that
we're gonna need. And in particular,
我们看一些关于合数模的算术事实
let's look at some arithmetic facts
modulo composites. So here we have our
这里我们有模N，N正好是两个质数的积
modulus N, which happens to be a product
of two primes, and you should be thinking
大家应该想到p和q，它们的大小差不多，因为
of P and Q as roughly equal size numbers,
since particular P and Q are both roughly
P和Q的大小差不多是N的平方根。那么两个大小差不多大
on the size of square root of N. So both
are roughly the same size. Recall that we
我们记Z_N，表示从0到N-1的所有整数的集合
denoted by ZN the set of integers from
zero to N minus one, and we said that we
我们说过，在Z_N上我们可以做模N加法和乘法。我们记Z_N^*
can do addition and multiplication module N. We denoted by ZN star the set of
表示Z_N上的乘法可逆元素。那么这些是全部的元素
invertible elements in ZN. So these are
all the elements, which have a modular
它们都有模逆。我们说过，x是可逆的
inverse. And we said that actually X is
invertible if and only if it's relatively
当且仅当x与N互质。进一步地，我还告诉过大家
Z_N^*中可逆元素的数目
prime to N. Moreover, I also told you that
the number of invertible elements in ZN
由这个函数ψ(N)表示。那么ψ(N)是Z_N^*中可逆元素的数目
star is denoted by this function phi(N). So phi(N)
is the number of invertible elements in ZN
我告诉过大家，当N是两个不同的质数的乘积时
star, And I told you that when N is a
product of two distinct primes, then in
那么事实上ψ(N)=(p-1)(q-1)，如果把它展开
fact phi(N) is equal to (P - 1) times (Q - 1) and if you extend that out, you
它就等于(N-p-q-1)。现在记得我说过
see that this is really equal to (N - P - Q + 1). Now remember that I said
p和q约为N的平方根大小，意味着
that P and Q are on the order of square
root of N which means that P + Q is
p+q也大约是N的平方根大小，意味着ψ(N)
also on the order of square root of N.
Which means that really phi(N) is on the
大小大约是N-2√N。那么换句话说，ψ(N)与N很接近
order of N minus two square root of N. So,
in other words, it's very, very close to
减去一个N的平方根
N. Basically, subtracting the square root
of N from a number, this is from, N is
这里N将是一个大数，约600十进制位
going to be a huge number in our case,
like 600 digits. And so subtracting from a
那么一个600位数减去一个600位数的平方根，也就是大约300位
600 digit number, the square root of that
600 digit number, namely a 300 digit
是很难影响这个数的大小的，意味着
number, hardly affects the size of the
number. Which means that phi(N) is really,
ψ(N)其实和N很接近，我想让大家记住
really, really close to N, and I want you
to remember that, because we will actually
因为我们现在会使用这点，那么ψ(N)很接近N的事实
be using this now and again. And so the
fact that phi(N) is really close to N, means
意味着如果我们选取模N中的随机元素，非常有可能
that if we choose a random element modulo
N It's very, very, very likely to be in ZN
这个元素也在Z_N^*中，非常不可能选择一个Z_N中的随机元素
star. So it's very unlikely that by
choosing a random element in ZN, we will
得到的元素却不是可逆的。好，那么记住这点
end up choosing an element that is not
invertable. Okay. So just remember that,
事实上几乎所有的Z_N中的元素都是可逆的
that in fact almost all elements in ZN are
actually invertible. And the last thing
最后我们需要的是欧拉定理，我们上周讲的
that we'll need is Euler's theorem, which
we covered last week, which basically says
这定理是说，对于Z_N^*中的任意元素x，如果我计算
x的ψ(N)次方，我会在Z_N中得到1
that for any element X in ZN star, if I
raise X to the power of phi(N), I get one, in
那么换句话说，我获得1模N，我会再说一遍
ZN. So in other words, I get 1 modulo N. I'll say it one more time because this
因为这个对接下来的内容至关重要。x^ψ(N)=1 mod N
is gonna be critical to what's coming.
Again X to the phi(N) is equal to 1 modulo
现在我们有了必要的背景知识，我们可以描述
N. So now that we have the necessary
background we can actually describe the
RSA陷门置换了。这是一个经典的密码学机制
RSA trapdoor permutation. This is a classic,
classic, classic construction in
首先于1977年在科学美国人上发表
cryptography that was first published in
Scientific American back in 1977, this is
这是密码学里的一篇著名论文。在那之后，已经35年了
a very well known article in cryptography.
And ever since then, this was 35 years
RSA陷门置换在密码学应用中被广泛使用
ago, the RSA trapdoor permutation has been used
extensively in cryptographic applications.
例如，SSL和TLS都使用了RSA，用于证书和密钥交换
For example, SSL and TLS use RSA both for
certificates and for key exchange. There
有很多安全的电子邮件系统和安全的文件系统，使用了RSA
are many secure email systems and secure
file systems that use RSA to encrypt
加密电子邮件和文件系统里的文件。这个系统里
emails and encrypt files in the file
system. And there are many, many, many
有很多其他应用。那么这是一个非常经典的密码学机制
other applications of this system. So this
is a very, very classic, crypto
我会给大家展示它是如何工作的。我应当说
construction, and I'll show you how it
works. I should say that RSA is named for
RSA由他的发明人R.Rivest，A.Shamir和L.Adleman命名
its inventors, Ron Rivest, Adi Shamir and
Len Adleman, who were all at MIT at the
他们在麻省理工做出了这一重要发现。
现在我们准备描述RSA陷门置换
time they made this important discovery.
So now we're ready to describe the RSA
为了做到这点，我必须描述这个密钥生成算法
trapdoor permutation. To do that, I have
to describe the key generation algorithm,
函数f和你函数f^-1。我们来看
the function ? and the function ??1.
So let's see. So the way the key
密钥生成算法如下工作：我们生成两个质数
generation algorithm works is as follows:
What we do is we generate two primes, P
p和q，每个大约是1000位，约300十进制位
and Q, each would be, say on the order of
1000 bits, so, you know, roughly 300
然后RSA模就是这两个质数的乘积
digits, and then the RSA modulus is simply
going to be the product of those two
接下来我们选取两个指数e和d
primes. The next thing we do is we pick
two exponents, e and d, such that e times
满足e乘d等于1模ψ(N)。这意味着e和d首先
d is 1 modulo phi(N). What this means is
that e and d first of all are relatively
必须与ψ(N)互质，其次，它们必须互为模ψ(N)的逆
prime to phi(N) and second of all they're
actually modular inverses of one another,
然后我们输出公钥为(N,e)
modulo phi(N). And then we output the public
key as the pair N,e and the
而私钥是(N,d)。我应该说一下这个指数e
secret key is the secret key N,d. I should mention that the exponent e,
这个e有时被称为加密指数
that the number e is sometimes called the
encryption exponent and the exponent d is
而指数d有时被叫做解密指数。大家会看到
sometimes called the decryption exponent.
And you'll see why I keep referring to
我马上会一直用这些指数。现在RSA函数本身的定义
these as exponents in just a second. Now
the way the RSA function itself is
是很简单的。为求简便，我将把它定义成
defined is really simple. For simplicity
I'm gonna define it as the function
从Z_N^*到Z_N^*的函数。这个函数
from ZN star to ZN star. And the way
the function is defined is simply given an
有输入x，我们只需取x，计算在Z_N中x的e次方
input X, all we do is we simply take X and
raise it to the power of e in ZN. So we
那么我们只需计算x^e mod N。就行了。解密时
just compute X to the e, modulo N. That's
it. And then to decrypt, what we do is we
我们只需给定输入y，计算y的d次方模N就行了
simply, given an input Y, we simply raise
Y to the power of d, modulo N. And that's
那么现在大家可以看到，为什么我要说指数e和d
it. So now you can see why as I refer to e
and d as exponents. They're the things
它们是x和y的指数。那么我们快速验证一下f^-1
that X and Y are being raised to. So let's
quickly verify that F inverse really does
确实是函数f的逆。那么我们看当我们计算y^d时会发生什么
invert the function F. So let's see what
happens when we compute Y to the d. So
假设y本身正好是RSA函数在某个值x处的值
suppose Y itself happens to be the RSA
function of some value X. In which case,
这时y^d就是RSA(x)^d，而x本身
what Y to the d is, is really RSA of X to
the power of d. While X by itself is
将变成x^e mod N，因此，y^d就是x^(ed) mod N
simply gonna be X to the e modulo N, And
therefore, Y to the d is simply X to the e
这里又使用了指数规则，将指数相乘了
times d modulo N. Again, just using rules
of exponentiation, the exponents multiply,
那么我们获得x^(ed)。关于e乘d我们知道什么？
so we get X to the e times d. But what do
we know about e times d? e times d we said
我们说过，e乘d是1模ψ(N)，这意味着存在某个整数k
is one modulo phi(N). And what that means is
there exists some integer such that e
满足ed = kψ(N)+1，这是ed = 1 mod ψ(N)的意义
times d is equal to K times phi(N) plus one.
This is what it means that e times d is
那么我们可以用kψ(N)+1替换ed
one modulo phi(N). So, we can simply replace e
times d by K times phi(N)+1. So, that's
那么我写在这。我们有x^(kψ(N)+1)
what I wrote here. So, we have X to the
power of K times phi(N)+1. But now again
现在再使用指数规则，我们可以重写这个式子，
变成(x^ψ(N))^k*x
just using rules of exponentiation, we can
re-write this as X to the power of phi(N) to
这与kψ(N)+1作为指数是一回事
the power of K times X. This is really the
same thing as K times phi(N)+1 as the
我只是把指数分到了不同的项上
exponent. I just kind of separated the
exponent into it's different components.
现在x^ψ(N)根据欧拉定理，我们知道ψ(N)=1
Now, X to the phi(N) by Euler's theorem, we know
that X to the phi(N) is equal to one. So what
那么整个乘积等于什么？由于x^ψ(N)=1
is this whole product equal to? Well since
X to the phi(N) is equal to one, one to
1的k次方是1，所以整个这一项就等于1
the K is also equal to one, so this whole
thing over here is simply equal to one.
我们留下的只有x了。所以我们刚刚证明了
And what we're left with is X. So what we
just proved is that if I take the output of
如果我取RSA函数的输出，然后计算它的d次方，我能得到x
the RSA function and raise it to the power
of 'd', I get back X. Which means that
这意味着计算d次方就是RSA的逆
raising to the power of 'd' basically
inverts the RSA function, which is what we
这是我们想证明的。那么完事了，这就是RSA函数的全部描述
wanted to show. So that's it, that's the
whole description of the function, we've
我们已经描述了密钥生成，陷门函数本身，即计算
described the key generation. The function
itself, which is simply raising things to
数的e次方模N，以及陷门函数的逆，即计算
the power of e modulo N, and the inversion
function which is simply raising things to
数的d次方模N。下个问题是，为什么这个函数是安全的？
the power of d, also modulo N. The next
question is, why is this function secure?
换句话说，为什么这个函数是单向的，如果我只有公钥
In other words, why is this function one
way if all I have is just a public key,
没有私钥的话？为了证明这个函数是单向的
but I don't have the secret key? And so to
argue that this function is one way we
我们表述这个RSA假设，告诉我们RSA函数
basically state the RSA assumption which
basically says that the RSA function is a
是一个单向置换。形式化地，我们说
one way permutation. And formally the way
we state that is that, basically for all
对所有有效的算法A，如果我生成两个指数p和q
efficient algorithms, A, it so happens
that if I generate two primes p and q,
随机的质数p和q，我把它们乘起来，获得模N
random primes p and q. I multiply them to
get to modulus N and then I choose a
然后我随机选择一个Z_N^*中的y，现在我给了模N，指数
random 'y' in ZN star. And now I give
the modulus, the exponent and this 'y' to
(这里的指数e由公钥指定)
和这个y给算法A，我会得到RSA在点y的逆的概率
algorithm A, the probability that I'll get
the inverse of RSA at the point Y, mainly
即得到y^(1/e)，真正的逆
I'll get Y to the power of one over E.
That's really what the inverse is. This
这个概率是可忽略的。那么这个假设叫做RSA假设
probability is negligible. So this
assumption is called the RSA assumption.
它是说，给定公钥，RSA是一个单向置换
It basically states that RSA is a one way
permutation just given the public key. And
因此，它是一个陷门置换，因为它有陷门
therefore, it is a trapdoor permutation
because it has a trapdoor. And makes this
(这里的陷门指的是私钥里的d)
这个陷门使得凡是知道陷门的人，可以很容易地求逆
easy to invert for anyone who knows the
trap door. So now that we have a secure
现在我们有了一个安全的陷门置换，我们可以
把这个陷门置换带入我们的公钥加密机制
trap door permutation, we can simply plug
that into our construction for public key
获得我们的第一个真实的公钥加密系统
encryption, and get our first real world
public key encryption system. And so what
那么我们就把这个RSA陷门置换带入ISO标准机制
we'll do is we'll simply plug the, the RSA
trapdoor permutation into the ISO standard
也就是我们上一节讲的机制。那么如果大家还记得
construction that we saw in the previous
segment. So, if you recall, that
那个机制是基于一个必须提供认证加密的对称加密系统的
construction was based on a symmetric
encryption system that had to provide
它还是基于一个哈希函数的
authenticated encryption. And it was also
based on a hash function. Then mapped
从RSA的角度看，这个哈希函数把Z_N里的元素
while transferring it into the world of
RSA, it maps elements in
映射到对称密钥系统的密钥
ZN, into secret keys for the
symmetric key system. And now the
现在加密机制的工作方式是容易描述的
way the encryption scheme works is really
easy to describe. Basically algorithm G
算法G就运行RSA的密钥生成算法，产生一个公钥和一个私钥
just runs the RSA key generation algorithm
and produces a public key and a secret
与之前一样。那么大家注意到，这个公钥包含了
key. Just as before. So you notice the
public key contains the encryption
加密指数，而这个私钥包含了解密指数
exponent and the secret key contains the
decryption exponent. And the way we
我们加密的过程如下：我们随机选择一个Z_N中的元素x
encrypt is as follows. Well, we're going
to choose a random X in ZN. We're going
我们对x应用RSA函数。我们先推导出一个对称密钥
to apply the RSA function to this X, we're
going to deduce a symmetric key from this
通过对x取哈希，那么我们计算H(x)以获得密钥k
X by hashing it, so we compute H of X to
obtain the key K, and then we output this
然后我们输出这个y和使用对称密钥k加密后的信息
Y along with the encryption of the message
under the symmetric key K. And in
在实际中，这个哈希函数H使用SHA-256实现
practice, the hash function H would be
just implemented just using SHA-256, and
大家会使用SHA-256的输出，来生成对称密钥
you would use the output of SHA-256 to
generate a symmetric key that could then
然后使用这个对称密钥作为对称加密的助手
be used for the symmetric encryption
assistant. So that's how we would encrypt
那么我们会加密，然后解密，与之前章节里别无二致
and then the way we would decrypt is
pretty much as we saw in the previous
首先，我们使用密钥
segment, where the first thing we would do
is we would use the secret key to invert
来求密文开头的逆，那么我们会计算y的RSA逆
the header of the ciphertext. So we would
compute RSA invert of Y, that would give
这会给我们值x，那么我们对x应用哈希函数
us the value X. Then we would apply the
hash function to X so that this would give
会得到密钥k。然后我们运行对称系统的解密算法
us the key K. And then we would run the
decryption algorithm for the symmetric
来解密密文，会产生最初的明文m
system on the ciphertext and that would
produce the original message m. And then
然后我们陈述上一节里的一个定理，是说
we stated a theorem in the previous
segment to say that if the RSA trapdoor
如果RSA陷门置换是安全的，对称加密机制
permutation is secure, Es and Ds, the
symmetric encryption scheme has
提供了认证加密，我们说过，H是随机神谕
provided authenticated encryption. And as
we said, H is just random oracle. It's,
H是某个从Z_N映射到密钥空间的随机函数。那么事实上
you know, kind of a random function from
ZN to the key space. Then, in fact, this
这个系统是选择密文安全的，是一个很好的可使用的公钥系统
system is chosen cipher text secure, and
is a good public key system to use.
那么现在我们有了第一个好的可使用的公钥系统
So now that we have our first example of a
good public key system to use, I wanna
我想快速地警告大家，不要用RSA去加密
quickly warn you about how not to use RSA
for encryption. And this again something
我们上一节已经讲过这点了。我这里再重复一遍
that we said in the previous segment. And
I'm going to repeat it here, except I'm
我要针对RSA再讲一遍。那么我想把这个叫做教科书RSA
going to make it specific to RSA. So
I'd like to call this, textbook RSA.
这是我们提到RSA加密时，第一个想到的方案
Which basically is the first thing that
comes to mind when you think about
私钥和公钥与之前一样
encrypting using RSA, namely, the secret
key and the public key will be as before.
但现在不是通过哈希函数来生成对称密钥
But now instead of running through, a hash
function to generate a symmetric key, what
我们直接使用RSA来加密给定的明文M
we would do is we would directly use RSA
to encrypt the given message M. And then
然后我们直接使用解密指数来解密密文
we would directly use the decryption
exponent to decrypt the cipher text and
获得明文M。我把这个叫做教科书RSA
obtain the plain text M. I'm going to call
this textbook RSA, because there are many
因为很多教科书就是这样描述RSA加密的，这是完全错误的
textbooks that describe RSA encryption in
this way. And this is completely wrong.
(比如Stinson的著名密码学教材第三版里的例子5.5)
这并不是RSA加密的工作过程，这是不安全的系统
This is not how RSA encryption works.
It's an insecure system. In particular,
(可能是受RSA原作者给出的例子影响，情有可原)
特别地，这是一个确定的加密，因此它不可能是语义安全的
it's deterministic encryption, and so it
can't possibly be semantically secure, but
事实上，有很多攻击存在，我待会就会给大家看一个
in fact there are many attacks exist that
I'm going to show you an attack in just a
但我想说清楚的一点是
minute, but the message that I want to
make clear here, is that RSA, all it is,
RSA是一个陷门置换，本身不是一个加密系统
is a trap door permutation. By itself
it's not an encryption system. You have to
大家必须用这个ISO标准为例，来完善它，使之成为
embellish it with this ISO standard for
example, to make it into an encryption
一个加密系统。而其本身仅为一个函数。
那么我们来看会发生什么错误
system. By itself, all it is, is just a
function. So let's see what goes wrong if
如果你试图使用教科书RSA，换句话说，
如果你试图直接使用RSA来加密一个明文
you try to use textbook RSA, In other
words, if you try to encrypt a message
我会给你一个网络世界中的攻击的例子
using RSA directly. And I'll give you an
example attack from the world of the web.
设想我们有一个网页服务器，这个服务器有RSA私钥
So imagine we have a web server. The web
server has an RSA secret key. Here's it's
私钥记为(N,d)。这里我们有一个网页浏览器，
浏览器试图与网页服务器建立起一个安全的会话
denoted by N and D. And here we have a web
browser who's trying to establish a secure
一个安全的SSL会话。那么SSL工作的方式是
session, a secure SSL session, with the web
server. So the way SSL works is that the
网页浏览器开始时发送这个客户端hello消息
web browser starts off by sending this
client hello message saying, hey, I want
我想和你建立一个安全会话。网页服务器回复一个
to set up a secure session with you. The
web server responds with a server hello
服务端hello消息，其中包含了服务器的公钥。
然后网页浏览器会生成一个随机数
message that contains the server's public
key. And then the web browser will go ahead
这个随机数叫做预备主密钥K
and generate a random what's called a
premaster secret K, it will encrypt the
它加密预备主密钥K，然后把结果以密文形式
premaster secret using K and send the
result in ciphertext over to the web
(这里不该说using，因为是直接使用RSA进行的加密)
发送给网页服务器。服务器会解密，然后也会获得K
server. The web server will decrypt and
then the web server will also get K, so
那么现在双方都有了共享密钥，他们可以使用它来安全会话
now the two have a shared key that they
can use to then secure a session between
那么我想告诉大家，如果我们直接使用RSA函数加密K
them. So I want to show you what goes
wrong if we directly use the RSA function
会发生什么错误。换句话说，如果K直接加密成
for encrypting K. In other words, if
directly K is encrypted as K to the e
K^e mod N的话，为了论证方便，我们假设K是一个64位密钥
modulo N. Just for the sake of argument
let's suppose that K is a 64-bit key.
我们把K当作范围从0到2^64的一个整数
We're going to treat K as an integer in
the range as zero to 2 to the 64.
更为精确地，2^64 - 1，现在我们做如下事情
More precisely two to the 64 minus one,
and now what we're going to do is the
首先，假设K正好能分解成几个差不多大小的数的乘积
following. First of all, suppose it so
happens that K factors into a product of
那么我们可以把K写成K1乘K2，K1和K2是整数
roughly equal sized numbers. So K we can
write as K1 times K2, where K1 and K2 are
比如说，两个都小于2的34次方。那么实际上
integers. And both are say less than two
to the 34. So, it turns out this happens
这有20%的概率会发生，那么5次中会有一次
with probability roughly twenty percent so
one in five times K can actually be
K可以被写成这样。但现在如果我们把这个K=K1*K2
written in this way. But, now if we plug
this K, K=K1 x K2 if we plug that into the
带入到定义密文的函数中，大家就会发现，
我们把K替换成K1乘K2
equation that defines the cipher text you
see that we can simply substitute K by K1 x k2
然后我们可以把K1移到另一边，这样我们会得到这个方程
and then we can move k1 to the other side.
So then we end up with this equation here,
即C/(K1^e)=K2^e。大家注意，如果我两边都乘以K1^e
namely C over K1 to the e is equal to K2 to the e. You notice if I multiply both
我得到C=(K1K2)^e
sides by K1 to the e, I get that C is
equal to K1 times K2 to the e,
就是这里的方程。我只是用K1*K2替换了K
which is precisely this equation here.
Okay, so all I did is I just replaced K by
然后除以K1^e。现在这个，大家看起来有点熟悉
K1 times K2 and then divided by K1 to the
e. So by now this should look familiar to
当然在这个方程中，我们有两个变量
you. So now we have two variables in this
equation, of course. C is known to the
攻击者知道C，知道e，也知道N
attacker, E is known to the attacker, and
N is known to the attacker. The two
这个方程里的两个变量是K1和K2，我们把它们
variables in this equation are K1 and
K2, and we've separated them into a
分在了方程的两边，因此我们现在可以利用这个方程
different side of the equation, and as a
result we can do now a meet in the middle
进行中间相遇攻击了。那么我们来进行中间相遇攻击
attack on this equation. So let's do the
meet in the middle attack. What we would
我们构建一张表，里面存放左边的所有可能值
do is we would build a table of all
possible values Of the left-hand side. So
C/(K1^e)的所有可能值，有2的34次方个
all possible values of C over K1 to the E,
there are 2 to the 34 of them. And then,
然后对右边所有的可能值，对K2^e的所有可能值
for all possible values on the right-hand
side, then for all possible values
我们检查这个值是否在我们第一步构建的表里
of K2 to the e, we're gonna check whether
this value here lives in the table that we
如果在，我们就找到了一个碰撞
constructed in step one. And if it is then
we found a collision, and basically we
我们就有了这个方程的一个解。那么
我们一旦找到了一个元素具有形式K2^e
have a solution to this equation. So as
soon as we find an element of the form K2
这个元素在我们第一步构建的表里面
to the E that lives in the table that
we built in step one, we've solved this
那么我们就已经解决了这个方程，并找到了K1和K2。
当然我们一旦找到K1和K2
equation and we found K1 and K2. And
of course once we found K1 and K2,
我们可以很容易地还原K，通过简单地相乘K1和K2
we can easily recover K simply by
multiplying them. So then we multiply K1
那么我们将K1乘K2，就能得到密钥K。我们就已经破解了
and K2 and we get, the secret key
K. Okay? So, we've broken, basically,
这个加密系统。要花多少时间？暴力地搜索
this, this encryption system. And how long
did it take? Well, by brute force, we
我们可以在2的64次方的时间里破解它，
通过简单地尝试所有可能的密钥
could have broken it in time 2 to the 64,
simply by trying all possible keys. But
但大家注意，这个攻击花了2的34次方的时间做第一步
this attack, you notice, it took 2 to
the 34 time for step number one. Well, it
其实它花的时间略多于2的34次方，
因为我们必须计算这些指数
took a little bit more than 2 to the 34,
'cause we had to do these exponentiations.
它花了2的34次方的时间做第二步，
同样地，用时略多于2的34次方
It took 2 to the 34 time for step two,
again slightly more than two to the 34
因为要做指数运算。那么我们说，整个算法用时2的40次方
because of the exponentiations. So let's
say that the whole algorithm took time two
关键在于，这个比2的64次方的时间少得多
to the 40. The point is that this is much,
much less time due to the 64. So here you
那么这里大家有了一个例子，如果你直接使用RSA加密
have an example. Where if you encrypt
using RSA directly, in other words you
换句话说，直接计算K^e mod N，而不是通过ISO标准
directly compute, K to the E, mod N,
instead of going through the ISO standard,
那么大家会获得一个攻击，可以比穷举快得多
for example, then you get an attack that
runs much faster than exhaustive search.
大家获得了一个用时2的40次方的攻击，远远快于2的64次方
You get an attack that runs in time two to
the 40, rather than time two to the 64.
好，那么这个可爱的例子揭示了，如果直接使用
Okay, so this is a cute example of how
things can break if you use the RSA
RSA陷门置换来加密明文，那么如何来破解系统的
trapdoor permutation directly to
encrypt a message. So the message to
那么这里需要记住的要点是，永远不要直接用RSA去加密
remember here, is never, ever, ever use
RSA directly to encrypt. You have to use to go
必须通过一个加密机制来使用它，比如ISO的标准
through an encryption mechanism. For
example, like the ISO standard. And in
事实上，下一节我们将看到其他使用RSA的方法
fact, in the next segment we are going to
see other ways of using RSA to build
来构建公钥加密
public key encryption.